Gabriel N. Camargo-Toledo

Cra 4 # 1 - 82, Casa 12, Camino La Balsa, Chía, 250001, Colombia

□ (+57) 3175316851 | ☑ gabriel.n.c.t182@gmail.com | 🛅 gabriel-n-camargo-toledo-02444384 | 🥞 gaborio123

'The way to cope with the future is to create it. (Ilya Prigogine)'

Summary.

Political scientist and data geek with knowledge in survey research and design, statistics, econometrics and statistical software development. With 11+ years of social science research, and experience on survey research, in academic settings, and for several non-profit and for-profit organizations, including being in charge of sample design, stratification and weighting. I also have 3+ years of teaching experience. I have the skills and interest in creating content for non-technical audiences based on quantitative and qualititative evidence about political and socioeconomic phenomena. I am proficient in different computational tools such as Stata, and R including the creation of R software packages. I have excellent communication skills in English and Spanish. I have shown my leadership and management skills in research and student groups and in leading research teams in a business setting.

Work Experience_

Sensata UX Research

SENIOR RESEARCHER

Aug. 2020 - Apr 24

- · Develop, lead, and analyze every step of the survey research process. This includes theoretical design, sampling design, questionnaire development and testing in different languages, data collection tracking and monitoring, cleaning, preparing and weighting data, and analyzing data to produce reports.
- · Develop software that extracts data from non-relational databases (MongoDB) and R packages to quickly prepare and analyze data from Sensata's own survey collection platform. This led to faster delivery of high-quality data to our customers from when data collection started to final microdata and report delivery. It also standardized the analysis done by the research team, allowing us to be flexible to the diverse methodological requirements of our different clients while maintaining the high quality of our research.
- Present research results understanding the needs of our customers and their level of expertise; to lead to a better data-driven decision-making
- · Organize and track online and offline survey collection processes, using our software to quickly make timely decisions to ensure high-quality data at the lowest possible cost.

Gimnasio Fontana

SOCIAL STUDIES TEACHER

Jul. 2019 - Jul. 2020

- · Taught 8th and 9th-grade social studies. I created engaging content and lessons, that taught the subject matter while leading students to think creatively, using different tools such as code and art to share knowledge.
- · Lead GFMun which coordinated and sponsored students on national UN models, and organized the internal model. This required thinking outside the box since it had to be done under COVID-19 lockdown.

Universidad Javeriana, International Relations Department

Aug. 2019 - Aug. 2020

INSTRUCTOR - QUANTITATIVE RESEARCH (UNDERGRAD)

- Taught introductory quantitative to International Relations students.
- · Focused on causal inference methods using observational data, using R programming language.
- During this time I also lead several undergraduate thesis, most of them using survey data.

World Bank. South Asia Data Lab

Bogotá, Colombia (remote)

SHORT TERM CONSULTANT

Prepared and organize metadata from income surveys from several South Asian countries.

Nashville, TN, USA

Dec. 2018 - Apr. 2019

Latin American Public Opinion Project (LAPOP), Vanderbilt University RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Aug. 2015 - Dec. 2018

• Create and audit graphs and statistical analysis for different in-house publications using Stata.

- Test, audit, and develop questionnaires in English and Spanish.
- Estimate survey response rates using R.
- Translate technical documents from English to Spanish and vice versa.

Observatorio de la Democracia, Universidad de los Andes

Bogotá, Colombia Apr. 2010, Jul. 2013

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- Created graphs and analysis for several publications.
- Co-wrote analysis of the impact of conditional cash transfer programs on 2010 elections.
- Streamlined the data management and analysis process organizing what was then an ad-hoc process using Stata.
- Established and managed a growing team of student researchers.

GABRIEL N. CAMARGO-TOLEDO · RÉSUMÉ JUNE 1, 2023

Book chapters

- Camargo Toledo, Gabriel N. & Ortega Gómez, Bibiana Astrid (2022) "La ley de cuotas en las elecciones nacionales de Colombia del 2018" in En reconfiguración permanente. Partidos y elecciones nacionales y subnacionales en Colombia, 2018-2019 Edited by Felipe Botero, Bibiana Ortega Gómez, Juan Federico Pino Uribe, and Laura Wills-Otero.
- Ortega Gómez, Bibiana Astrid & Camargo Toledo, Gabriel N. (2015) "Ley de cuotas en Colombia: Elecciones al Congreso de la República 2014-2018." in *Elecciones en Colombia, 2014. ¿Representaciones Fragmentadas?* Edited by Freddy Barrero, and Margarita Batlle.
- Ortega Gómez, Bibiana Astrid & Camargo Toledo, Gabriel N. "La Nueva Ley de Cuotas en Colombia. El Caso de las Asambleas Departamentales, 2007-2011." in *Política y Territoria. Análisis de la Elecciones Subnacionales en Colombia, 2011* Edited by Laura Wills Otero y Margarita Batlle.

Other publications.

- Araos, Ana María; Bohóquez, Maria FernandaM Camargo-Toledo, Gabriel N; del Portillo, Marcela & Rodríguez, Juan Sebastian. "Entre
 empresarios y líderes sociales. Afectos, ideología y polarización en Colombia México, Argentina y Brasil", 2022, Sensata UX Research
- Warner, Zach. & Camargo-Toledo, Gabriel N. "How Does LAPOP Calculate Response Rates?", 2018, Methodological Note 5
- Camargo Toledo, Gabriel N. & Rodríguez Raga, Juan Carlos. "Familias en Acción y Preferencias Políticas. Colombia 2010.", Apuntes de cultura política 1

Conference presentations

- "When Presidents are coaches: World Cup results affect citizens' evaluation of the government." With Oscar Castorena. Annual meeting of the Midwest Political Science Association. Chicago, IL, USA, April 2017.
- "Political sophistication and clarity of responsibility: understanding conditional economic vote." Annual meeting of the Midwest Political Science Association. Chicago, IL, USA, April 2016.
- "When a gender quota is (not) effective. Colombia legislative elections 2010-2014." With Bibiana Astrid Ortega. VIII Congreso latinoamericano de ciencia política. Lima, Perú, July 2015
- "Presidential Charisma and (Anti)Democratic Values in Latin America." With Alejandra Ortiz and Juan Carlos Rodríguez-Raga. Annual meeting of the Midwest Political Science Association. Chicago, IL, USA, April 2013.
- "Institutions, Accountability and Conditional Economic Voting in Latin America. A Hierarchical Analysis." With Miguel García-Sanchez and Juan Carlos Rodríguez-Raga. Annual meeting of the American Political Science Association. Seattle, WA, USA, September 2011.

Education

M.A. POLITICAL SCIENCE

Vanderbilt University

With a focus on comparative politics and political methodology.

Universidad de Los Andes Bogotá, Colombia

B.A. POLITICAL SCIENCE

Jan. 2007 - Oct. 2011

• Took several undergraduate and master level economic courses.

Additional activities

2017-2018 **Co-President**, Latin American Student Association, Vanderbilt University

Nashville, TN, USA

2016-2017 **Co-President**, Graduate Student Political Science Association, Vanderbilt University

Nashville, TN, USA

Skills

Statistics Expert

Data Visualization Expert

R and Stata Expert

Bayesian modelling - Stan Advanced

Spanish Native

English Proficient (C2-Toefl)

Other interests _

• Scuba diver, Advanced Open Water PADI

Nashville, TN, USA Aug 2013 - May. 2019